Zhenlin An

BIOGRAPHY

Website: anplus.github.io Email: an.zhenlin@outlook.com LinkedIn: zhenlin-an-209500b4

My research interests are broadly including wireless systems and networking, mobile computing, wireless sensing, and wireless security and privacy. Currently, I focus on NextG AI-driven wireless channel modeling and prediction, digital twin and wireless localization.

• Keywords: Wireless Systems and Networking, Indoor Localization and Wireless Sensing, Acoustic, Embedded System, Low-power IoT Systems, Wireless Security

EDUCATION

The Hong Kong Polytechnic University

Hong Kong SAR, China

Ph.D. in Computer Science

2017.9-2021.10

- Chief Supervisor: Dr. Lei Yang, Co-supervisor: Prof. Jiannong Cao (IEEE Fellow)
- Thesis: "On Cross-Technology Mutualism in the Internet of Things: Communication and Localization"

Dalian University of Technology

Dalian, China

B.E. degree in Electronic Engineering and Information System

2013.9-2017.7

- Supervisor: Prof. Chengan Guo

Professional Experience

University of Pittsburgh

Pittsburgh, PA, US

2024.7-Present

Postdoctoral Associate at Department of Computer Science

- Advised by Dr. Longfei Shangguan, Prof. Kyle Jamieson (InterDigtial: John Kaewell and Philip Pietraski)

Princeton University

Princeton, NJ, US

Postdoctoral Research Associate at Department of Computer Science

2023.12-2024.7

- Advised by Prof. Kyle Jamieson, Dr. Longfei Shangguan (InterDigital: John Kaewell and Philip Pietraski)
- Develop a <u>full-differentiable ray tracing system and neural networks</u> for radio environment model and channel prediction <u>using tensorflow and Nvidia Sionna.</u>

The Hong Kong Polytechnic University

Hong Kong SAR, China

Postdoctoral Fellow Advised by Dr. Lei Yang, funded by Postdoc Matching Fund

2021.11-2023.11

- Multi-modality Deep learning localization system for BLE and RFID
- Design neural RF ray tracing for channel prediction and localization: Best paper runner-up in MobiCom'23.
- Wireless Security (hardware fingerprints for RFID and NFC (Develop an USRP-emulated RFID reader to collect raw backscatter data and classification algorithm.); inaudible command injection on wireless charger.
- Develop acoustic backscatter hardware and software. PZT-based acoustic energy harvest and communication.

Huawei Technologies

Shenzhen, Guangdong, CN

Research Intern in 2012

2020.6-2020.12

- Develop CNN based RFID localization platform with distributed antenna array. (One patent)
- Develop beamforming algorithm for RFID systems in complex warehouses (reading rate > 99.9%). (One patent)

The Hong Kong Polytechnic University

Hong Kong SAR, China

Research Intern at Department of Computing

2016.11-2017.3

- Advised by Dr. Lei Yang

RESEARCH PROJECTS

1. Wireless Sensing and Digital Twin

- Physics-guided AI wireless channel estimation and radio environment modelling (MobiCom'23, MobiSys'24)
- Deep learning and Antenna Array Localization Platform (MobiSys'20, INFOCOM'22, TOSN'22)
- Ultrasound Positioning System for smartphone (MobiCom'19 and TMC'20)
- Multi-modal Sensing: fusing RF and image sensor (SECON'20, TOSN'22)

2. Backscatter Communication and Sensing System

- Acoustic Backscatter System for RF-disable environment (e.g., Structure Health Monitoring) (SIGCOMM'22)
- High throughput RFID MAC layer design (MobiCom'17, TON'19, INFOCOM'19, TON'20, NSDI'24)
- Long Range Backscatter Communication (INFOCOM'21, INFOCOM'23)

3. Cross-technology Communication System

- Transformer NN for PHY translation: WiFi to ZigBee and BLE (Sensys'23)
- NFC to Camera Communication (MobiCom'23), Fusing NFC Antenna and QRCodes (MobiCom'21)
- AM Radio and UHF RFID communication (INFOCOM'20, TON'22)
- WiFi and UHF RFID communication (MobiCom'18, TON'20)

4. IoT Security & Privacy

- Inaudible Command Injection and Protection (S&P'23)
- Hardware Fingerprint Authentication in UHF RFID tag (MobiCom'22, SECON'23) and NFC (INFOCOM'23)

Awards and Honours

2023
2023
2023
2022
2022
2020
2019
2019
2018
2017
2016
2016

PUBLICATIONS

[†]Co-primary author, [‡] Co-corresponding author, Google Scholar Page

Conference Articles

- Zhenlin An, Longfei Shangguan, John Kaewell, Philip Pietraski, Kyle Jamieson
 RadioTwin: A Digital Building Material Twin for Wideband, Cross-link, Cross-band Wireless Channel Prediction
 In Submission, 2024
- 2. Zheng Gong, **Zhenlin An**[‡], Donghui Dai, Jingyu Tong, Sicong Liao, Lei Yang[‡] Enabling Cross-Medium Wireless Networks with Miniature Mechanical Antennas In Proc. of **ACM MobiCom**, Washington, D.C., USA, 2024.
- 3. Jingyu Tong, **Zhenlin An**, Xiaopeng Zhao, Sicong Liao, Lei Yang In-Sensor Machine Learning: Radio Frequency Neural Networks for Wireless Sensing In Proc. of **ACM MobiHoc**, 2024.

- 4. Xueyuan Yang, **Zhenlin An**, Qingrui Pan, Lei Yang, Dangyuan Lei, Yulong Fan Binary Optical Machine Learning: Million-Scale Physical Neural Networks with Nano Neurons In Proc. of **ACM MobiCom**, Washington, D.C., USA, 2024.
- Donghui Dai, Zhenlin An[‡], Zheng Gong, Qingrui Pan, Lei Yang[‡]
 RFID+: Spatially Controllable Identification of UHF RFIDs via Controlled Magnetic Fields
 In USENIX NSDI, Santa Clara, USA, 2024.
- Xiaopeng Zhao, Shen Wang, Zhenlin An, Lei Yang Crowdsourced Geospatial Intelligence: Constructing 3D Urban Maps with Satellitic Radiance Fields In Proc. of ACM IMWUT/UbiComp, 2024.
- Yanni Yang, Genglin Wang, Zhenlin An, Pengfei Hu, Xiuzhen Cheng, Guoming Zhang RF-Parrot: Wireless Eavesdropping on Wired Audio In Proc. of IEEE INFOCOM 2024.
- 8. Xiaopeng Zhao, Guosheng Wang, **Zhenlin An**, Qingrui Pan, Lei Yang Understanding Localization by a Tailored GPT In Proc. of **ACM MobiSys**, Tokyo, Japan, 2024.
- Donghui Dai[†], Zhenlin An[†], Lei Yang Inducing Wireless Chargers to Voice Out for Inaudible Command Attacks In IEEE Security & Privacy (Oakland) 2023.
- Xiaopeng Zhao, Zhenlin An[‡], Qingrui Pan, Lei Yang[‡]
 NeRF2: Neural Radio-Frequency Radiance Fields
 In Proc. of ACM MobiCom, Madrid, Spain, Oct 2-6, 2023. (Best Paper Award Runner-up)
- 11. Donghui Dai, **Zhenlin An**[‡], Qingrui Pan, Lei Yang[‡]
 MagCode: NFC-Enabled Barcodes for NFC-Disabled Smartphones
 In Proc. of **ACM MobiCom**, Madrid, Spain, Oct 2-6, 2023.
- 12. Sicong Liao, **Zhenlin An**, Qingrui Pan, Xiaopeng Zhao, Jingyu Tong, Lei Yang[‡] XiTuXi: Sealing the Gaps in Cross-Technology Communication by Neural Machine Transition In Proc. of **ACM Sensys**, Istanbul, Turkiye, Nov 13-15, 2023.
- Xueyuan Yang, Zhenlin An, Xiaopeng Zhao, Lei Yang Transfer Beamforming via Beamforming for Transfer In Proc. of IEEE INFOCOM, New York area, USA, May 17 - 20, 2023.
- Yanni Yang, Jiannong Cao, Zhenlin An, Yanwen Wang, Pengfei Hu, Guoming Zhang NFChain: A Practical Fingerprinting Scheme for NFC Tag Authentication In Proc. of IEEE INFOCOM, New York area, USA, May 17 - 20, 2023.
- 15. Qingrui Pan, Zhenlin An, Xiaopeng Zhao, Lei Yang Revisiting Backscatter Frequency Drifts for Fingerprinting RFIDs: A Perspective of Frequency Resolution In Proc. of IEEE SECON, Madrid, Spain, Sep. 11-14, 2023.(Best Paper Award)
- Qingrui Pan[†], Zhenlin An[†], Xueyuan Yang, Xiaopeng Zhao, Lei Yang RF-DNA: Large-Scale Physical-layer Identifications of RFIDs via Dual Natural Attributes In Proc. of ACM MobiCom, Sydney, Australia, Oct 17-22, 2022.
- 17. Zheng Gong[†], Lubing Han[†], **Zhenlin An**[‡], Lei Yang[‡], Siqi Ding, Yu Xiang Empowering Smart Buildings with Self-Sensing Concrete for Structural Health Monitoring In Proc. of **ACM SIGCOMM**, Amsterdam, the Netherlands, Aug 22-26, 2022.
- 18. Qingrui Pan, **Zhenlin An**, Xiaopeng Zhao and Lei Yang LSAB: Enhancing Spatio-Temporal Efficiency of AoA Tracking Systems In Proc. of **IEEE INFOCOM**, 2-5 May 2022.

- Zhenlin An, Qiongzheng Lin, Xiaopeng Zhao, Lei Yang, Dongjiang Zheng, Guiqing Wu, Shan Chang One Tag, Two Codes: Identifying Optical Barcodes with NFC In Proc. of ACM MobiCom, New Orleands, USA, Oct 25-29, 2021.
- Zhenlin An, Qiongzheng Lin, Qingrui Pan, Lei Yang
 Turbocharging Deep Backscatter Through Constructive Power Surges with a Single RF Source
 In Proc. of IEEE INFOCOM, May 10-13 2021.
- 21. **Zhenlin An**[†], Qiongzheng Lin[†], Ping Li, Lei Yang General-Purpose Deep Tracking Platform across Protocols for the Internet of Things In Proc. of **ACM MobiSys**, Toronto, Canada, June 15-19, 2020.
- 22. **Zhenlin An**, Qiongzheng Lin, Lei Yang, Lei Xie Activating Wireless Voice for E-Toll Collection Systems with Zero Start-up Cost In Proc. of **IEEE INFOCOM**, Beijing, China, April 27-30 2020.
- Qiongzheng Lin, Lei Yang, Zhenlin An, Yi Guo, Ping Li RFCamera: Identifying RFIDs in Pixel Dimension
 In Proc. of IEEE SECON, Combo, Italy, June 22-25, 2020. (Best Paper Award)
- 24. Qiongzheng Lin[†], **Zhenlin An**[†], Lei Yang Rebooting Ultrasonic Positioning Systems for Ultrasound-Incapable Smart Devices In Proc. of **ACM MobiCom**, Los Cabos, Mexico, Oct 21-25, 2019.
- 25. Zhenlin An, Qiongzheng Lin, Lei Yang, Wei Lou Embracing Tag Collisions: Acquiring Bloom Filters across RFIDs in Physical Layer In Proc. of IEEE INFOCOM, Paris, April 29 - May 2, 2019.
- 26. Ping Li, Zhenlin An, Lei Yang, Panlong Yang Towards Physical-Layer Vibration Sensing with RFIDs In Proc. of IEEE INFOCOM, Paris, France, April 29 - May 2, 2019.
- 27. Zhenlin An, Qiongzheng Lin, Lei Yang Cross-Frequency Communication: Near-Field Identification of UHF RFIDs with WiFi! In Proc. of ACM MobiCom, New Delhi, India, Oct 29 - Nov 2, 2018.
- 28. Lei Yang, Qiongzheng Lin, Chunhui Duan, **Zhenlin An**Analog On-tag Hashing: Towards Selective Reading as Hash Primitives for COTS Gen2 RFID Systems
 In Proc. of **ACM MobiCom**, Snowbird, UT, USA, Oct. 16-20, 2017.

Journal Articles

- 29. Donghui Dai, **Zhenlin An**, Qingrui Pan, Lei Yang Harnessing NFC to Generate Standard Optical Barcodes for NFC-Missing Smartphones in **IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing**, 2024.
- 30. Yanni Yang, Zhenlin An, Jiannong Cao, Yanwen Wang, Pengfei Hu, Guoming Zhang, Xiuzhen Cheng Jump out of Resonance: A Practical NFC Tag Fingerprinting Scheme in IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing, 2024.
- 31. Xiaopeng Zhao, **Zhenlin An**, Qingrui Pan, Lei Yang Understanding Wireless Channels Through NeRF2 in **ACM GetMobile** (Research Highlights), 2024.
- 32. Xiaopeng Zhao, Shen Wang, **Zhenlin An**, Lei Yang Crowdsourced Geospatial Intelligence: Constructing 3D Urban Maps with Satellitic Radiance Fields in **Proc.** of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies, 2024.
- 33. Yanni Yang, Pengfei Hu, Jun Luo, **Zhenlin An**⊠, Jiannong Cao, Dongxiao Yu, Xiuzhen Cheng Romeo: Fault Detection of Rotating Machinery Via Fine-Grained Mmwave Velocity Signature in **IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing**, 2024.

- 34. Xiaopeng Zhao, Guosheng Wang, **Zhenlin An**, Qingrui Pan, Qiongzheng Lin, and Lei Yang Pushing the Boundaries of High-Precision AoA Estimation with Enhanced Phase Estimation Protocol in **IEEE Internet of Things Journal**, 2024.
- 35. Qingrui Pan, **Zhenlin An**, Xiaopeng Zhao, Lei Yang The Power of Precision: High-Resolution Backscatter Frequency Drift in RFID Identification in **IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing**, 2023.
- 36. Xueyuan Yang, **Zhenlin An**, Xiaopeng Zhao, Lei Yang Transfer Beamforming via Beamforming for Transfer in **IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing**, Oct 2023.
- 37. Yue Yu, Yepeng Yao, Zhewei Liu, **Zhenlin An**, Biyu Chen, Liang Chen, Ruizhi Chen A Bi-LSTM approach for modelling movement uncertainty of crowdsourced human trajectories under complex urban environments, in **International Journal of Applied Earth Observation and Geoinformation**, Aug 2023.
- 38. **Zhenlin An**, Qiongzheng Lin, Lei Yang, Lei Xie
 Tagcaster: Activating Wireless Voice of Electronic Toll Collection Systems with Zero Start-up Cost in **IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking** (IEEE/ACM ToN), Apr 2022.
- 39. Qingrui Pan, **Zhenlin An**, Qiongzheng Lin, Lei Yang LSAB: Enhancing Spatio-Temporal Efficiency of AoA Tracking Systems in **ACM Transactions on Sensor Network** (ACM TOSN), Apr 2022.
- Zhenlin An[†], Qiongzheng Lin[†], Lei Yang, Yi Guo and Ping Li Localizing RFIDs in Pixel Dimensions in ACM Transactions on Sensor Network (ACM TOSN), Feb 2022.
- 41. **Zhenlin An**, Lei Yang, Qiongzheng Lin Identifying UHF RFIDs in Range of Readers with WiFi in **IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking** (IEEE/ACM ToN), Feb 2021.
- 42. Wenzhong Shi, Zhewei Liu, **Zhenlin An**, Pengfei Chen RegNet: a neural network model for predicting regional desirability with VGI data in **International Journal of Geographical Information Science** (IJGIS), 2021
- 43. **Zhenlin An**, Qiongzheng Lin, Lei Yang, Wei Lou and Lei Xie Acquiring Bloom Filters across Commercial RFIDs in Physical Layer in **IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking** (IEEE/ACM ToN), May 2020.
- 44. **Zhenlin An**[†], Qiongzheng Lin[†], Lei Yang, Yi Guo Revitalizing Ultrasonic Positioning Systems for Ultrasound-Incapable Smart Devices in **IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing** (IEEE TMC), February 2020.
- 45. Ping Li, **Zhenlin An**, Lei Yang, Panlong Yang, QiongZheng Lin RFID Harmonic for Vibration Sensing in **IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing** (IEEE TMC), January 2019.
- 46. Qiongzheng Lin, Lei Yang, Chunhui Duan, **Zhenlin An**Tash: Towards Selective Reading as Hashing Primitives for Gen2 RFIDs in **IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking** (IEEE/ACM ToN), April 2019.

Demos

- Daidong hui, Zhenlin An, Qingrui Pan, Lei Yang
 Demo: MagCode: Bringing NFC Feature to All Smartphones
 In Proc. of ACM MobiCom, Madrid, Spain, Oct 2-6, 2023
- 48. Jingyu Tong, **Zhenlin An**, Xiaopeng Zhao, Sicong Liao, Lei Yang Demo: Radio Frequency Neural Networks for Wireless Sensing In Proc. of **ACM MobiCom**, Madrid, Spain, Oct 2-6, 2023 (**Graduate Award**)

- 49. Daidong hui, **Zhenlin An**, Lei Yang
 - Demo: Inducing Wireless Chargers to Voice Out, Project Page

In Proc. of ACM MobiCom, Sydney, Australia, Oct 17-22, 2022 (Best Demo Award Runner-up)

50. Zheng Gong, **Zhenlin An**, Jingyu Tong, Donghui Dai, Lei Yang

Demo: Constructing Smart Buildings with In-concrete Backscatter Networks, Project Page
In Prog. of ACM MobiCom, Sydney, Australia, Oct 17, 22, 2022 (Bost Domo Ayang Bunno)

In Proc. of ACM MobiCom, Sydney, Australia, Oct 17-22, 2022 (Best Demo Award Runner-up)

51. **Zhenlin An**, Qiongzheng Lin, Lei Yang

Demo: Activating Wireless Voice for E-Toll Collection Systems with Zero Start-up Cost In Proc. of **ACM MobiCom**, Los Cabos, Mexico, Oct 21-25, 2019

52. Zhenlin An, Qiongzheng Lin, Lei Yang

Demo: Near-Field Identification of UHF RFIDs with WiFi!

In Proc. of ACM MobiCom, New Delhi, India, Oct 29-Nov 2, 2018 (Best Demo Award Runner-up)

Patents

- 53. Donghui Dai, **Zhenlin An**, Qingrui Pan, Lei Yang. CN Patents No. CN116132956B (2023): Near field communication method and system based on camera magnetic field interference
- 54. Yanni Yang, Sen Jia, Dongxiao Yu, Peng Wang, **Zhenlin An**, Huafeng Xu, Jiannong Cao, Entao Sun, Chao Du. CN Patents No. CN115436938A (2023): Passive signal measuring device and measuring method based on millimeter wave radar
- 55. Qingrui Pan, **Zhenlin An**, Lei Yang. CN Patents No. CN115377702A (2022): Antenna array optimization method, device, terminal and storage medium
- 56. **Zhenlin An**, Xueyuan Yang, Lei Yang, Yuan Li, Hong Liu, Jia Jia, Renhui Sun. CN Patents No. CN116263868A (2021): Communication system, communication method and communication device
- 57. Xiaopeng Zhao, **Zhenlin An**, Lei Yang, Jia Jia, Renhui Sun, Hong Liu. CN Patents No. CN116437435A (2021): Positioning server, positioning method and back reflection communication system
- 58. Qiongzheng Lin, **Zhenlin An**, Lei Yang. CN Patents No. CN113050022B (2019): Image positioning method and device based on rotary antenna and terminal equipment

Professional Activities

Referee for submissions to journals:

- ACM/IEEE Transactions on Networking (2018-2024)
- IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing (2022-2024)
- IEEE Internet of Things Journal (2019-2024)
- IEEE Transactions on Dependable and Secure Computing (2023-2024)
- ACM Transactions on Sensor Networks (2022)
- ACM Transactions on Internet of Things (2023)
- IEEE Embedded Systems Letters (2023)
- IEEE Journal of Radio Frequency Identification (2024)
- IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics and Security (2024)
- IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering (2024)
- Nature Science Reports (2024)
- International Journal of Communication Systems (2023-2024)
- Journal of Computer Science and Technology (2022)

Referee for submissions to conference:

- 2024 IEEE ICPADS, ICA3PP, ACM MobiCom Artifacts
- 2023 IEEE ICPADS, ACM MobiCom Artifacts, ACM MobiArch
- 2022 IEEE ICPADS, EAI MobiQuitous, ACM SIGCOMM SRC Juror

Editor Service:

- 2024 Electronics, Special Issue: Ubiquitous Computing and Mobile Computing, Information Page
- 2023 Sensors, Special Issue: Signal Processing for Sensors, Information Page

TEACHING

Teaching Assistant at PolyU (Lecturer: Dr. Lei Yang)
 Web Application Design and Development (COMP 3421)

Spring 2021

Teaching Assistant at PolyU (Lecturer: Dr. Lei Yang)
 Internet Computing and Applications (COMP 5322)

Fall 2020, Spring 2020

• Teaching Assistant at PolyU (Lecturer: Prof. Guiling Wang) Crowdfunding and E-finance (COMP 4141) Fall 2019

Teaching Assistant at PolyU (Lecturer: Dr. Lei Yang)
 Enterprise Web and Internet Computing for Managers (COMP 5321)

Fall 2018

• Teaching Assistant at PolyU (Lecturer: Dr. Lei Yang) Mobile Computing (COMP 4342) Spring 2019, Spring 2018, Fall 2017

• Teaching Assistant at DUT (Lecturer: Yingjie Zhang) Microcomputer Assembly and Commissioning 2014-2017

FUNDINGS

• co-PI: Physical Neural Networks, PolyU Internal Funding, HKD 100M, 2023-2025

INVITED TALK

- 2024-10-08, "Neural Radio-Frequency Radiance Fields", Rensselaer Polytechnic Instituter, host: Ish Kumar Jain
- 2024-09-27, "Advancements in Wireless Sensing", Palantir Technologies, host: Dr. Di Wang
- 2024-07-18, "Learning to understand radio environment", Microsoft, host: Prof. Lili Qiu
- 2024-06-18, "RadioTwin", Interdigital Long Island Research Center, host: John Kaewell
- 2023-06-30, "Neural Radio Frequency Radiance Field", Dalian University of Technology, host: Prof. Chi Lin

SKILLS

- Programming: Python; Matlab; C/C++; Verilog HDL
- Platform: Tensorflow, Pytorch; Microcontroller (MSP430, ESP32, Arduino); PCB design (Altium Designer); Antenna Simulation and Design (CST); Android Studio;
- Tools: VNA, Spectrum Analyzer, USRP and GNU Radio
- Domain Knowledge: array signal processing, wireless networking, machine learning, embedded system

Reference

- Dr. Lei Yang, (Ph.D. Advisor), Email: young@tagsys.org
 Associate Professor in The Hong Kong Polytechnic University
- Dr. Jiannong Cao, (Ph.D. Co-advisor), Email: csjcao@comp.polyu.edu.hk Chair Professor in The Hong Kong Polytechnic University
- Dr. Longfei Shangguan, (Postdoc Co-advisor in Princeton), Email: longfei@pitt.edu Assistant Professor in University of Pittsburgh